wa alaikum assalamu alaikum wa rahmatullahi wa barakatuhu
our book on these days, ayamul jum'a, on the days of jum'a, after salatul asri, is kitab al-kaba'ir
kitab al-kaba'ir was written by al-imam al-zahabi, rahimahullah, abu abdillah, muhammad ibn ahmad
that well-known scholar of the recitation of the Quran, that well-known scholar of hadith,
that well-known scholar of tarikh, and very many other branches of knowledge in this deen
al-imam al-zahabi, rahimahullah, looked at a verse of the Quran where Allah said
subhanahu wa ta'ala, in tajtanibu kaba'iru ma tunhawna anhu, nu kafir ankum say'atikum
wa nu dkhilkum mudkhalan kareema, in tajtanibu kaba'iru ma tunhawna anhu, oh mankind if you abstain
oh people of iman if you abstain in tajtanibu kaba'iru ma tunhawna anhu, if you abstain from those that are kaba'ir
from the things that we have prohibited you, from the things that we have prohibited you, some of them are kaba'ir
in tajtanibu kaba'iru ma tunhawna anhu, if you abstain from those that are kaba'ir
amongst the things that you have been prohibited from, Allah said the reward is that nu kafir anhum say'atikum
your smaller, your relatively lesser sins, nu kafir, Allah said nu kafir anhum, we will atone for you
your smaller sins, those sins that are of lesser gravity than al kaba'ir, they are also called alsogha'ir
they are also called allamam, nu kafir anhum say'atikum, they are also called say'at
we will make you also gain a honorable entrance into that home of esteem al jannah
these verse made al imam al zahabi to now begin to say okay what are those kaba'ir
if abstinence from kaba'ir will make us gain atonement for sogha'ir, and will make us gain al jannah
abstain from kaba'ir, you gain two things, atonement for your sogha'ir and admission into al jannah
he said rahimahu Allah, bata'iyyan alayna al fahsoo, it becomes absolutely incumbent on us to research and find out
we should find out about kaba'ir, what are these kaba'ir, which things make kaba'ir
so that the muslim can abstain from them, if you don't know kaba'ir, how will you abstain from them
we have studied them one after the other until we got to al kabiratul salisata'ashra
al kabiratul salisata'ashra, the 13th amongst the kaba'ir, the 13th
and that is al imamul ghashul ir'iyatihi abzalimul jabbar
someone who is an imam, is a leader of the people, is their president, commander in chief
or their governor, or their regional head, or their administrative head
every person who heads any group of people, as we are reading one of the hadiths
the prophet said, alayhi salatu was salam, that's hadith number 94
ma amin amiri ash-sharatin, there is none who heads just a group of ten
even if it were ten people, ma amin amiri ash-sharatin
there is not anyone who leads, who heads, who controls any ten group of people
the ulama say, he just mentioned ten lit-taqlil, to show that no matter how small
to these matters, we are not just talking about the head of a country
we are also talking about the imam of a masjid, we are also talking about the head of a university
we are also talking about the head of a department, whether in the university or in the secondary school
we are even also talking about the headmaster, every person who leads a group of people
and then he is al-gha-shu, this person, he deceives them, he cheats them
and he is vali-mun, he is unfortunately unfair and unjust and dirty towards them
and then he adds something to that, al-jabbu, he is jabbar, very tyrannical and oppressive
it is from the deeds of al-kaba'ir, so a kabira from amongst the kaba'ir is that
the imam becomes gha-shun-li ra-iyatihi, deceptive, he is leading the people and he is misleading them
he deceives them, he deludes them, and then he is unfair and unjust
and then he is tyrannical, in anyone or all of these cases, anyone who rules the people
becoming unjust, misleading them, treating them unfairly and unjustly
this is from al-kaba'ir, it means these are from the deeds
that can prevent the individual from gaining entrance into al-jannah
al-imam al-abdahabi rahimahullah mentioned a number of verses
so far from the kaba'ir that we have read, we are on the 13th
this point al-kaba'ir to the 13th, it has the largest number of hadith
we have read from it, hadith number 89, 1991, up to hadith number 94
we have also studied 95 and 96, so we can start our lesson, bi'inillah
from hadith number 95, the prophet said in this dua
that was reported from him by our mother Aisha and it's a hadith that is collected by al-imam al-muslim
the prophet said
anyone who is given the job, the duty, in any form in this ummah
no matter the job, you are given the job of an imam in your masjid
you are given the job of a principal in your school
you are given the job of a headmaster in your school
you are given the job of a head of department
you are the head of the law chamber
you are the head, the clinical head
or the head of department in the hospital
or the dean of the faculty
anybody who is placed in charge of anything
he has been given any particular job in the affairs of this ummah
and then he takes it easy with the people
he makes life easy for them
he supports them
he helps them
he overlooks their faults
he makes things easy for them
this kind of a person, be easy with him
look at this dua
anyone placed in charge of anything in this ummah
and then he is easy
he is nice to them
he rules them well
he is fair to them
be easy with him
be kind towards him
O Allah show your favors on him
O Allah anyone who makes things difficult for the people
if you are a president you make things difficult for the people
if you are a governor you make things difficult for the people
you are a minister
because
you have been placed with something
a particular job in this ummah has been placed on your neck
so if you maltreat the people
be tough on him
if he is harsh on the people
if he is coerced towards the people
be harsh with him too
be coerced with him
if he punishes the people
punish him too
if he distiffs the people
give him what is due to him
from his punishment
this is a dua and a warning
the dua inside it is that
if you are a just ruler
if you are a just imam
if you are a just controller
wherever you are
you control something from the affairs of the generality of the people
and you do it well
O Allah be easy, be kind with these kinds of people
O Allah those who make things difficult for the people
punish them
this was the dua of the prophet Muhammad
and the dua has two wings
the wing of goodness
for those who rule with goodness
and the wing of punishment
for those who are unfair to the generality of the people
may Allah protect us
there is one big lesson here
these days we usually talk about
good governance, good governance
you can see
the prophet prayed
the anger of Allah
and the punishment of Allah upon those who punish you
it is compulsory that any Muslim
any Muslim who takes up
the position of leadership
maybe as a governor
maybe as a commissioner
maybe as a head of a parastatal
maybe as a head of an agency of government
and then you are harsh
you punish the people
there is a dua of the prophet
that will come to you because of your behaviour
and when you are nice
you are kind to us
you favour us
you are easy with us
O Allah
be easy with these kinds of people
this dua, this hadith
was collected by our mother Aisha
and it occurs
in the Sahih Muslim
in hadith number 96
the prophet said
the imam said
and the prophet also said
that
there will be leaders
there will be
sinful people
people who will be
disobeying Allah
oppressive
they will be disobeying Allah
and then they will be tyrannical
these leaders shall come
the prophet said
some leaders will come
there will be leaders who will be
they will be sinful
or righteous people
they will be very
very very wicked
in another report
of this hadith
the prophet said
they will be telling you to do things
that they will never do
they are oppressive
wicked, disobedient to Allah
the prophet said
anyone who affirms
what they are
in front of lies
and deceit
they are wicked leaders
disobedient to Allah
they are always going beyond the limits of
Allah's dictates
very disobedient
they steal the money of the people
they punish the people
they rule unjustly
subhanallah
in fact some of these rulers
unfortunately
they will be people of zina
they will be people of
alcohol
taking drugs
all kinds of acts of disobedience
will be with them
in fact some of them may not be
observing salah
they may not even be observing
and paying zakawat
they are people of wickedness
may Allah protect us
oppressive
the prophet said
therefore
anyone amongst you
people
who colludes with them
or connives with them
upon their lies
and you support them
upon the injustice
that they spread on the surface
of the earth
the prophet said
such a person
is not bad of me
is not upon
my sunnah
and I declare
freedom from him
such a person
who
he
affirms
and supports
leaders who are disobedient
he is supporting
them
because of him
he is supporting them
upon the lies that they propagate
and he is helping them upon
injustice
there is something to understand here
it means
if such a person works with them
but he does not support
them upon their lies
and he does not support them
about their injustice
this is not what the prophet is talking about
if you do not
support them upon the lies
and you are not supporting
them upon the injustice
that they perpetrate
you are not in this condition
you are not the one that is
asked about in this hadith
but if you do
the prophet said
the one who does that
such a person is not of me
is not following
my line of conduct
and I am not
from him, I am not with him
I am such a person
he will not come
to me
he will not reach me
at Al-Hawd
what is Al-Hawd?
Al-Hawd is the pool
a large pool
pool of
a drink
that drink
the prophet Muhammad
sallallahu alayhi wa sallam
told us about it
that it is
the pool of
the prophet sallallahu alayhi wa sallam
is
do we know musk
is a kind of a perfume
so the pool of the prophet
sallallahu alayhi wa sallam
sweet smelling
it smells so well
better than the
smell of musk
and then it is
whiter than
whiter than the
the milk
in fact in some reports it says also that
it is
it is also far sweeter
than what?
than honey
this is a gift from
Allah to all the prophets of Allah
alayhi wa sallam
on the day of Qiyamah
but our own prophet will have
his own too
that is Al-Hawd
that Allah has preserved for him
any person who supports
his
oppressive rulers
Umara
these
Ulama, these Umara
who are faqaqa
sinful people, unrighteous
Jawara
who are oppressive
if you support them you will not drink from Al-Hawd
the prophet said
alayhi wa sallam
he will not come to me at Al-Hawd
they will be prevented
because from the things that will happen
at Al-Hawd on the day of Qiyamah
some people too, when they saw the prophet
they will want to
go there and take from this drink
but they will be prevented
the prophet will say
alayhi wa sallam
these people are my people, why are you preventing them?
the angels will say
you don't know
what they started
what they became after you left
you don't know
but they became something else
you left them up on Sunnah
you left them up on
supporting
Al-Adl
but they became supporters
of what?
of Ulama
so for that matter
they will not be allowed to take from Al-Hawd
so it's a big
big big thing
to support
and affirm the lies
of rulers
this is a summon
for our brothers
Muslims who participate
in the democratic politics
that we know
they support their party
when they know that the party is lying
and deceiving the people
they still support it, they say it's our party
and they know that what they are saying
is a lie
they still support it, they say it's our party
and they know that the party is
upon zulm, injustice
wa'ana hum ala zulm
the heads, the leaders
are upon zulm, you are supporting it
because it is your party
don't worry this thing
act of big big big thing
for which
you'll be punished on the day of
Qiyamah because you'll be
kept away from Al-Hawd
therefore we adjure them
to make tawbah
and avoid these kinds of
behaviours
again the prophet said
there will be
he's talking about something that will come
later
there will be
rulers, rulers shall
come, who are they?
they are
sinful people
they are people of
oppression and aggression
they rule with trouble
may Allah protect us
the prophet said
anyone who
affirms the lie that these
rulers will be lying
wa'ana hum ala zulm
and support
them upon the injustice
that they will be perpetrating
that kind of a person is not
part of me
and I'm not part of that person
if the prophet says he's not part
of a person and that person
is not part of him, so who is
the person with?
the person is with sinful people that
he was helping and supporting
upon sinfulness and upon
their zulm
health, the third punishment
is that that person will not
participate and partake
in al-haut on the day
of qiyamah, this hadith
that we have read
it has been reported by six companions
of the prophet
it was reported by
it was reported
by
it was also reported
it was also
reported by
radiya-allahu-anhum
al-imam al-nasai
al-imam al-tirimidhi
manu-hibban
al-imam al-tabrani
we all report this hadith
that a hadith is widely reported
it has a meaning
It's either that the Prophet Sallallahu Alaihi Wasallam was repeating it, or that large
number of people repeated it.
It also repeated it from the Prophet Muhammad at the same time, and so they were telling
the people.
It was a common thing, all these companions were telling the people, telling the people.
What were they telling the people?
There will be leaders who are sinful people and oppressive.
Anyone who affirms, who inclines towards them upon the lie that they are lying.
Anyone who supports them upon their injustice.
That kind of a person is not part of me, and I declare, disconnect myself from that kind
of a person.
Such a person will never be with me on the day of Qiyamah.
That is Hadith number 96.
In Hadith number 97, Al-Imam al-Dhahabi said,
The Prophet Sallallahu Alaihi Wasallam said,
The Prophet said Sallallahu Alaihi Wasallam,
And this Hadith was reported by that well known companion, the most handsome companion
amongst the companions, Jareer ibn Abdullah al-Bajali.
Very handsome amongst the companions, Jareer ibn Abdullah al-Bajali reported that the Prophet
Sallallahu Alaihi Wasallam said,
There is not any group of people that act upon sins amongst them, a group of people.
Amongst them people are sinful, sinful, sinful.
And these people, they are more in number, they are more honorable, they are the leaders
in the community, and they are larger in number than those few ones amongst them that are
acting upon sinfulness, a group of people, maybe a community, maybe a state, maybe a
country.
There are some of us, some of the people in that country or in that community.
So some people are committing sins amongst us, in our own country, Nigeria.
Some people have unfortunately made themselves become bandits, some people are kidnappers,
some people are armed robbers.
Some people, yes, they are in government, but they are stealing the money of the government.
Some people, yes, they are in government, they will not discharge their duties to the
people unless they are bribed.
The Prophet said, But you know there are the rest of us.
I believe that the large majority of Nigerians are innocent people.
The larger majority are good people.
Those who control and perpetrate evil are not more than those who don't commit and perpetrate
evil.
The Prophet said, This larger majority, if they begin to look at the
smaller group and they look at them, they do not attempt to change the situation.
So in the northern states and in many of the parts of the country, they are bandits.
If the larger majority close their eyes, they don't do anything, they just cross their fingers
and fold their arms.
They do not do anything to it.
The Prophet said, Allah will send a punishment that will go around everybody.
If a people, you are in a community, some people are committing evil and you keep quiet,
Allah will send down the punishment and it will go around everybody.
Both those who are directly involved and those who have refused to do anything.
In our religion, Islam, it is prohibited that we see evil and we refuse to do anything.
You refuse to do anything.
You look away and see if it does not concern you.
Look at the various young people in the society today, upon Yahu, upon alcohol, upon various
kinds of deviations and then you sit down, you refuse to do anything.
The Prophet said, Allah will soon send down a punishment that will go around everybody.
So it is not lawful that you are in a place, you are in a community, people are committing
evil and you keep quiet.
How about if those committing that evil, they are the rulers?
It's not lawful to keep quiet when the generality of the people are committing evil.
How about when those committing these evils, they are those who should stop evil in the
society.
So there must be efforts, there must be efforts to ensure that people do what is right in
the community.
Islam does not allow that evil is spread in the society and then we keep quiet.
The same way in our homes, in our families, in our schools, the university, in our states,
in our community, as we said, these matters are not restricted to the national scenarios
alone.
Everywhere you find people.
The Prophet said, there is not a people that some people are committing sins amongst them.
And this larger number of people, they are more honorable, they are more powerful, they
are more influential and larger in number.
Much more than those committing that evil.
Then they chose to look the other way around.
They will not change anything.
Allah will spread a punishment that will go around everybody.
So when people kept quiet about banditry, banditry is going around everywhere.
When people kept quiet about kidnapping, may Allah protect us, these evils are spreading.
When people keep quiet about Zina, Zina will spread.
When people keep quiet about male irresponsibility at home towards their wives, male irresponsibility,
husband irresponsibility will go around.
When people keep quiet about women's regular audacious disobedience to their husband, then
more women will do it.
Whatever people commit and is bad and people keep quiet, Allah will send down a punishment
and it will go around everybody.
Beg Allah to protect us.
Beg Allah to protect us, to protect our children, to protect our homes.
May Allah protect our wives from all these evils.
No man should have his wife not praying and then he keeps quiet.
No man should have his children, they don't pray and then you keep quiet.
Your children don't wear hijab and you keep quiet.
Your wife does not wear hijab and you keep quiet.
Or that your wife has other deviations, whether of character or of thinking and then you keep quiet.
Allah will send down a punishment and it will go around everybody.
Beg Allah to protect all of us.
In Hadith number 98, Hadith we just read, we said it is from the Hadith of Jarir ibn Abdullah al-Bajali.
It was collected by Imam Ahmad in his Musnad.
Imam al-Tabrani also collected it in Al-Mu'ajam al-Kabir.
And it is an authentic Hadith.
The Hadith that shall follow is Hadith number 98.
And it's from the Hadith of Abu Mimsa al-Ash'ari.
It occurs in Sahih al-Bukhari.
It also occurs in Sunan al-Tirmidhi.
It also occurs in the Sunan of al-Imam ibn Majah.
But this report we are reading, it was collected by Abdullah ibn Mas'ud.
And it was reported from him by his son.
Abdullah ibn Mas'ud had a boy Abu Ubaidah.
He was a very young boy when ibn Mas'ud died.
He happens to be the only son that Abdullah ibn Mas'ud had.
His name was Abu Ubaidah.
The knowledge, all the documentation of Hadith that Abdullah ibn Mas'ud had,
he kept it in the house for that boy.
But the boy was very young when he died.
So amongst the scholars of Hadith,
some of them will rule the reports of Abu Ubaidah from Abdullah ibn Mas'ud as non-corporate.
Why? He had no good luck before his father died.
So he did not really sit down to learn from ibn Mas'ud.
So some say no.
If we are sure that what he got and was reporting from his father
were from the documents that his father had kept as a learned person, as a scholar.
Because one of the biggest scholars amongst the companions was Abdullah ibn Mas'ud.
In fact, some of the scholars said that he is the most learned companion
as far as the sciences of Syria is concerned.
The most learned companion was Abdullah ibn Mas'ud.
He said so about himself.
He said, I am the most learned about the Quran.
So the scholars say if we are certain that what Abu Ubaidah was reporting were from the documents
he collected from his father inside their house,
then it is a thief he took that knowledge directly from his father.
What is correct? There are a lot of things regarding this issue.
But what is most apparent with Allah is that the reports of Abu Ubaidah from Abdullah ibn Mas'ud
they are Muttasila, they are Sahihah.
The Isnad is Muttasil.
So here Al Imam al-Dhahabi said,
Oh Rahima Ghullah, Waroa Abu Ubaidah, Ibn Abdullah ibn Mas'udin and Abi.
Imam al-Dhahabi said, Abu Ubaidah reported from Abdullah ibn Mas'ud,
and from his father who said, Kuala Rasulullah Sallallahu Alaihi Wasallam.
The Prophet Muhammad Sallallahu Alaihi Wasallam said,
Ekhwa we are reading from Hadith number 98.
What we have on the screen is Hadith number 97.
We are reading Hadith number 98.
It said, Waroa Abu Ubaidah, Ibn Abdullah ibn Mas'udin and Abi,
all Kuala Rasulullah Sallallahu Alaihi Wasallam.
The Prophet Muhammad Sallallahu Alaihi Wasallam said,
Walladhi nafthi bi yadihi, I swear by Allah and my soul is in his hands.
I swear by the one that is holding my soul.
Oh you Muslims, you either command goodness,
you either command the people to act upon righteousness,
and you definitely prohibit people from evil.
And you hold on the hand of those who commit evil in the society.
You'd rather commanded goodness.
And you rather prohibit people from evil.
You'd rather grab the hand of the one who is doing something bad.
You'd rather push him, encourage him, adjure him, encourage him,
command him to do what is right.
You'd rather push him, encourage him, to do what is right,
if you don't do all these things.
The other alternative that you have is that
La yadribanna Allahu bi kulu bi ba'dhikum ala ba'dh.
Oh la yadribanna Allahu bi kulu bi ba'dhikum ala ba'dh.
The alternative you have is that
Yadribanna Allahu bi kulu bi ba'dhikum ala ba'dh.
Allah will set the hearts of some of you against the others.
If you don't make al-amru bil ma'ruf,
if you don't make al-nahyuan al-munkar,
if you don't hold back the hand of the Musi,
wa la ta'akhu dhunna ala yadil Musi,
oh that, wa la ta'aturunna hu ala al-Haqqi apra,
oh that you necessarily push him and encourage him towards Haqq,
if you don't do these things.
La yadribanna Allahu bi kulu bi ba'dhikum ala ba'dh.
Oh you Muslims, Allah will turn the hearts of some of you against the others.
You will hate yourself Muslims,
if you refuse to make al-amru bil ma'ruf,
wa al-nahyuan al-munkar,
wa al-akhz ala yadil Musi.
The Prophet said, sallallahu alaihi wa sallam,
la yadribanna Allahu bi kulu bi ba'dhikum ala ba'dh.
He also said, wa la ta'aturunna hu ala al-Haqqi apra.
You should push this man to the truth,
encourage him upon the truth.
Teach him the truth, enlighten him about the truth.
If you don't do these things, Allah will cause you to hate yourselves.
Thumma yalaanukum.
Then he will curse you.
Kama la'anahum.
Just like Allah cursed them.
Who are these them?
Ya'ni Bani Israel.
That is Bani Israel.
Ala lisani Dawudah wa Isa ibn Maryam.
The way Allah cursed Bani Israel,
upon the tongues of Dawud and Isa ibn Maryam.
That is the way Allah will curse you too.
This is a warning from us, the people of demand.
If we don't encourage people, command them to do what is right.
Ikhwa, we all have a duty to be commanding people to do what is right,
and to be preventing them, making them avoid what is wrong.
Or that you should hold the hand of someone doing evil.
Someone wants to do it, to commit an evil.
Hold his hand, don't let him continue.
The Prophet salallahu alaihi wa sallam, he had told us that
...
If you are in the position of authority, you saw someone doing something bad,
stop him! Give the command, stop!
Hold him hand, if you don't do this.
...
Then you begin to encourage, you push, you push, you push,
you adjure the person to do what is right.
The alternative to all of these is that
...
Allah will curse the hearts of some of you to pun against the others.
Meaning that you will hate yourself.
After that Allah will curse you.
...
The way Allah curse Bani Israel upon the tongue of
Dawood and Isa.
Remember that Allah mentioned that to us in Surah Al-Ma'idah.
...
Bani Israel were cursed upon the tongue of Dawood.
Dawood cursed Bani Israel.
Isa, alaihi wa sallam, he also cursed Bani Israel.
The two of them cursed Bani Israel.
Why did they curse them?
Allah says ...
They were very sinful people.
...
They went beyond the limits of Allah.
When Allah sets a limit, they violate it.
They were cursed.
They were sinful people violating the limits of Allah.
Allah says ...
At that time these people, Bani Israel,
...
When they violated the limits of Allah,
others who are not violating, who saw it,
...
They will not tell them, stop what you are doing.
What you are doing is bad.
No, they will not stop them.
They will not stop them.
...
It's a thing not to stop evil.
You see, you have the ability.
...
Stop it with your hand if you are capable.
And if you are not,
...
If the individual is not able, because of authority, to stop it.
You should speak against it now.
And if you are still not able, may Allah protect us.
You should hate it with your heart.
Hating it with your heart.
You hate that, that kind of a thing never happened.
And that is from the weakest.
May Allah protect us.
When you don't care,
people are committing Zinania, you don't care.
People are drinking alcohol, committing fornication.
People are not observing Salat.
Men are careless,
not taking care of their homes.
Women have become something else.
Behaving like the women of the days of Jahiliyyah.
In their dressing and in their thoughts and in their behaviors.
And then you keep quiet, it's a sin.
It's a sin.
How about in the face of all of these evils,
it is the ruler that has kept quiet.
In the face of banditry, the ruler kept quiet.
In the face of kidnapping, the ruler kept quiet.
In fact, is one encouraging, maybe alcohol,
maybe gambling, maybe betting,
maybe riba, the ruler encourages.
If the rank and file of the people, the held responsible,
how about the ruler,
who should ensure that
there is no sinfulness upon the surface of that.
So this is from the aspects of Zulm on injustice from the rulers
towards their followers.
May Allah protect us.
I think we can take Hadith number 99 today.
Al-Imam al-Dhahabi said,
Aghlab ibn Tamim reported these hadiths from him.
Al-Aghlab is weak reporter of hadith,
who come back to it.
Al-Aghlab ibn Tamim said,
That is Abu al-Hasan.
He is reporting from Muawiyah ibn al-Qurra,
that well-known tabi'i.
Is Abu Ali al-Muzani.
This hadith, this is not is da'if.
The isnaad is da'if.
Al-Aghlab ibn Tamim himself is da'if.
As al-Imam al-Dhahabi said,
But the hadith has shawahid, suqawwi.
It has corroborating evidences,
that shows that it is sahih.
What did the prophet say?
The prophet said,
He said,
There are two groups of people in my ummah.
By shafa'a, by intercession,
special intercession,
because the prophet has two.
The shafa'a to the suqra.
The shafa'a to the kubra is al-maqam al-mahmoud.
That one is for everybody.
Muslim, kafir, mushrik.
Everybody will enjoy from the shafa'a to the kubra.
So this shafa'a here is what?
The shafa'a to the suqra.
That one is meant for some Muslims.
The prophet will make, he has different forms of shafa'a
under the suqra, different types.
Where the prophet will beg Allah to forgive some people.
As much as this second kind of shafa'a, suqra,
It will not reach these two groups of people.
The first one, sultan ghaloum ghasoum.
The ruler who is ghaloum, unjust.
Ghasoum, jabbarun anit.
Wicked, coerced among the rulers.
Very oppressive.
Tyrannical ruler.
Ghaloum is an unjust person.
Ghasoum is a wicked tyrannical ruler.
Sultanun, ghaloumun, ghasoum.
La dana luhu shafa'a atu al rasuli.
Sallallahu alayhi wa ala salam.
The intercession, special intercession of the prophet
will not reach him on the day of qiyam.
Because of this is evil.
It is ghaloumun, ghasoum.
Sultanun, ghaloumun, ghasoum.
The head, the ruler, the authority,
who is unfair, who is unjust, who is ghasoum.
Wicked and tyrannical.
May Allah protect all of us.
The second person, wa ghalin fideen.
Ghalin fideen barikun minhum.
Ghalin fideen.
The one who goes into extremes in the matters of the religion.
Is an extremist in the matters of the religion.
How? I give you one small example.
One of the places where the prophet sallallahu alayhi wa ala salam
mentioned clear extremism in the deen
was a person who was selecting stones
that were bigger than the tip of the small finger
on the day of stoning the Jamarads.
He was picking big stones.
People said, it's ghalou.
Yes, you are to stone.
But these stones have gone beyond the stones
that you have been commanded to stone.
So when a person goes beyond limits.
Let me give us another example.
Yes, we are encouraged to observe qiyamun laid.
The prophet sallallahu alayhi wa ala salam told us about qiyamun laid.
In a lot of ahadith, how about the one who does not sleep?
He prays throughout the night.
This is ghalou fideen.
It's ghalou fideen, not to sleep at all, it's ghalou.
The same way we are encouraged to fast during the daytime, are we?
How about the one who every day is fasting?
Every day is fasting.
So look at him.
Every day he is fasting during daytime.
Every day he is on qiyamun laid.
He is not sleeping.
The prophet condemned it, sallallahu alayhi wa ala salam.
Another aspect of ghalou fideen.
A man has a wife and he never comes near her.
Or a woman who never allows her husband to come near her.
Why?
She is busy with ibadah.
I'm busy with ibadah.
And all of these, these are aspects of ghalou fideen.
You see that ghalou, the basics of that thing will be there.
But you'll be doing it in a manner that goes beyond limits.
Like fasting.
Yes, we should fast.
Beyond limit.
No fasting should go beyond fast a day, live a day.
That's so mudawud.
Except you fast three days in a month.
Maybe one at the beginning, one at the middle, one at the end.
Or you fast three straight days.
Whether at the beginning or at the middle or at the end.
These fasts are allowed.
For that a man is fasting every day of the month.
The only time you can do that is in Ramadan.
Except maybe the first ten days of Zulhija again.
Those ones are straight.
And even in that you are going to exempt two days from those first ten days of Zulhija.
The day of Nahar, the tenth day.
Because we have been prohibited from fasting on the tenth day of Zulhija.
You are also going to exempt a Saturday.
Because we have also been prohibited not to fast on Saturday.
Except a fast that is compulsory.
So all these are aspects of gulu.
A person goes beyond limits.
So he chooses not to ever break his fast.
Every day he's fasting.
As if it's Ramadan.
It's gulu fitting.
Or every day he's making kiamu led.
From Isha after Isha to Fajr.
Every day.
Let's not forget that the Prophet Sallallahu Alaihi Wasallam.
One of the companions was reported to him.
The wife reported to the brother who came to visit him.
In Medina.
And that one went to report to the Prophet Sallallahu Alaihi Wasallam.
This companion, that was Abdullah Ibn Amr al-As.
He did notice to sleep in the night.
And he would fast every day.
So his wife was feeling.
He would not come near the wife.
The Prophet didn't like it Sallallahu Alaihi Wasallam.
Something similar to that was reported about Abul Zerrin al-Ghifari also.
So Ekhwa.
Those who go beyond limits.
Ghalin Fidin.
We just explained Gulu Fidin.
For example fasting throughout the day time.
Never breaking fast.
Or never observing sleep.
Not sleeping.
Wa inna li jasadika alayka haqqan.
And your body has a right over you.
So sleep sometimes.
Wake up sometimes.
Some people abandon their wives.
Some women abandon their husbands.
And making kiamu led.
And fasting.
So that's why the husband cannot come near her.
That's why she can't cook for her husband.
This Gulu.
So the Prophet said alayhi salatu wassalam.
So in Fadim, in Ummati ila tana luhu ma shafa'ati.
Two groups of people in my ummah.
My special Shafa'a.
Mentioned for special people in special situations will not reach them.
The first one.
Sultanun zhaloumun ghashoum.
The Sultan.
The President.
The Governor.
The head.
The one with constituted authority.
But he is zhaloum.
Very wickedly unjust.
Ghashoum.
He is wicked.
Jabbar.
Wicked.
The Shafa'a of the Prophet will not reach him.
Alayhi salatu wassalam.
Wa ghalim fi deen.
And those who go beyond limits in the maqas of their religion.
Yushhidu alayhim.
Yushhadu alayhim wa yutabarra'u minhum.
These people.
Aw yushhadu alayhim wa yutabarra'u minhum.
The Prophet salallahu alayhi wa alayhi wassalam.
He will see them.
And he will disconnect himself from them.
Salallahu alayhi wa alayhi wassalam.
The ruler who is unjust and wicked to the people.
And those who go beyond limits in the maqas of their deen.
May Allah protect all of us.
This hadith occurs in the maujam of al-Imam al-Tabrani.
We said that this is not as weak.
But the hadith is tzahir.
So al-Imam al-Bahabi said, aghlabu dha'if.
Yani al-aghlab ibn Tamim.
He's a weak reporter of hadith.
Wa qod'u wa'u ibn al-Mubarak.
But this report has also been collected by al-Imam ibn al-Mubarak.
He said...
Using a similar thing of report.
Al-Imam al-Bahabi said...
It was mentioned that we don't know who he was.
But there are other bigger reports.
Like that of al-Imam ibn al-Adeel.
Who mentioned that...
So muna'i, his reports are Hasan.
But that's why al-Imam al-Bahabi said...
It is not known who he was.
Ibn al-Adeel has spoken earlier that we know him.
Al-Adeel shows that no matter how well-grounded you are,
some things will miss you.
You say you don't know.
Others say we know it.
People had known it before you.
But the point of reference here is that...
The head, the imam, the leader, the president, the governor,
who is unjust and wicked,
they will not gain the Shafa'ah of the Prophet,
sallallahu alayhi wa sallam, the day of Ki'aam.
May Allah protect all of us from this evil.
The evil of being a wicked leader and head.
Wicked principal.
Wicked HM.
And facts, wicked husband.
All of these come under this category.
Allah, we beg your protection, protect us.
Ya'zal jalal walaykoum.
I think we can look at the questions,
if we have one or two questions,
before we call it the day about the Rahman.
Do we have a question?
Or we just call it the day about the Rahman?
I just saw now that the time has been fast spent.
About the Rahman.
About the Rahman, are you there?
Okay, we can call it the day today.
Ameen.
Should we call it the day today?
Okay.
We come back to class on this issue.
Assalamu alaikum wa rahmatullahi wa barakatuhu.
Wa alaikum wa salamu alaikum wa barakatuhu.
Assalamu alaikum wa barakatuhu.
Ameen.